Crime, Prisons, and Reform Schools Collection, 1850-1977
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Crime, prisons, and reform schools collection
1850-1977
MS 424
2 boxes, 2 books (8 linear inches.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Documents the activities and experiences of female criminals, the efforts of social scientists to understand them, the work of prison reformers to improve their treatment, and the changing approaches and methods used by the state to manage them. Material includes printed material, correspondence, drawings, reports, and unpublished papers that focus on the United States and England.
The Crime, Prisons, and Reform Schools Collection documents the activities and experiences of female criminals, the efforts of social scientists to understand them, the work of prison reformers to improve their treatment, and the changing approaches and methods used by the state to manage them. Types of material include articles, correspondence, drawings, leaflets, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, promotional material, reports, and unpublished papers that focus on the United States and England and span the period from 1857 to 1977.
The collection includes some unique 19th century material such as correspondence relating to the founding of the Maine Industrial School for Girls (1862-1890), correspondence of prison reformer Miriam Van Waters (1930-1969), and one letter from Dorothea Dix (1882). Other material includes an undated typescript by a Dr. Tenebaum titled "The Riddle of a Woman," and an unpublished course paper by a Hampshire College student titled "Women in Prisons" (1972).
The bulk the collection consists of printed material. There are a large number of newspaper clippings and magazine articles that profile jailed women, analyze patterns of female crime, advocate better treatment of women prisoners, or describe new methods for punishing/rehabilitating women who violate the law. Most of these are dated from the 1960s to the 1970s, but a few are from the late 19th and early 20th centuries. Also included are annual reports and promotional material from organizations and programs that address the needs of women in the criminal justice system. Organizations include the Pennsylvania Program for Woman and Girl Offenders, the Fortune Society, Aid to Incarcerated Women, and the American Civil Liberties Union. Other printed sources in the collection include leaflets for anti-prison rallies, excerpts from the Congressional Record, and reports from state agencies.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions to collection are expected.
History of the Collection
Materials in this subject collection were purchased or given to the Sophia Smith Collection by various donors.
Search Terms
Female juvenile delinquents--History; Female offenders--History; Prison reformers--History--Sources; Prisons--History--Sources; Reformatories for women--United States--History; Women prisoners--History--Sources; Women social reformers--United States; Dix, Dorothea Lynde, 1802-1887; Van Waters, Miriam; Maine Industrial School for Girls (Hallowell, Maine)--History
- Bibliography, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Crime
  - Clippings, 1972-74 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Articles and other printed material, 1875, 1970-77 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - National Association of Women in Criminal Justice News, 1975-80 (Box 1, Folder 3a)
- Prisoners
  - Clippings, 1968-77 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Pictures, 1854, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Creative writing publications, 1974, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 5a)
  - Massachusetts, Governor's Commission on the Status of Women, Educational Task Force report: The Female Offender by Kay Bourne, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Pennsylvania Program for Women and Girl Offenders
    - General, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Inside/Outside, 1975-77 (Box 1, Folder 7a)
  - Women's Prison Association: printed material, 1957, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Pamphlets, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Unpublished papers, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Articles and other printed material, 1971-84 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The Woman Offender Report, May/Jun-Nov/Dec 1975 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Maine Industrial School for Girls
  - Resolution presented to the Maine House of Representatives (draft), 1867; clipping, undated (Box 2, Folder 12a)
  - Correspondence re: establishment, 1862-67 (Box 2, Folder 12b)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1880-1900 (Box 2, Folder 12c)
- Prison reform
  - General, 1969, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Dorothea Dix, 1850, 1882, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Margery Fry, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Sarah Martin, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Miriam Van Waters: correspondence, clippings and articles, 1930, 1966-69, undated (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
- Books on Shelf
  - Mathilda Wrede of Finland, Friend of Prisoners by Lilian Stevenson 1925
  - Rebels in the Streets: The Story of New York's Girls' Gangs by Kitty Hanson 1964